A Guide to the Rockefeller Brothers Fund records, Special Studies Project, RG 4 FA387
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Brothers Fund records, Special Studies Project, RG 4
1956-1964
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Brothers Fund
Kissinger, Henry
FA387
28 Cubic Feet
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated to the RAC by the Rockefeller Brothers Fund.
Biographical / Historical
The Rockefeller Brothers Fund Special Studies Project was inspired by Nelson Rockefeller, who served as President during most of the period of major activity. The purpose of the Special Studies was "to define the major problems and opportunities" facing the United States in the late 1950s, "to clarify national purposes and objectives...", and to develop principles which could serve as the basis of national policy.
To effect this aim, Henry Kissinger was chosen to serve as Director. Mr. Kissinger coordinated the solicitation, criticism, and editing of papers from a host of specialists in many fields, including history, area studies, economics, political science, and sociology. Many of these papers were used, in some measure, as the basis of discussion by the subpanels for which the papers were written. The papers and discussion sessions resulted in final reports by each panel, and these reports were published under the title "Prospect for America: the Rockefeller Panel Reports."
Scope and Contents
The records of the Rockefeller Brothers Fund Special Studies Project document the administrative and intellectual history of the project. The Special Studies Project collection constitutes a rich, but by no means comprehensive, source for the intellectual history of American domestic and foreign policy from 1945 to approximately 1960. Papers and criticisms of papers were contributed to the Project by leading academic and government authorities. Although an examination of these materials will not normally show the development over time of a writer's ideas, some files include a writer's older pieces. The papers prepared for the Special Studies Project are invariably thorough expositions of the contributor's views in the late 1950s.
This study was undertaken in the latter 1950s and was published in 1960. A number of Project participants became members of the Kennedy Administration. In addition, letters and memoranda to and by Henry Kissinger, and editorial comments by Mr. Kissinger, appear throughout these records. Most of these items are of a routine administrative nature, but there are some letters and memoranda by Mr. Kissinger which include substantive comments about foreign policy and panel papers.
Arrangement
The Special Studies Project record group is divided into ten series, listed below. The title that follows the subpanel number represents the name of the subpanel. The title in parentheses represents the title of the subpanel's report as it appears in "Prospect for America."
Series A - Subpanel I: International Objectives and Strategies (The Mid-Century Challenge to U.S. Foreign Policy)
Series B - Subpanel II: International Security Objectives and Strategy (International Security: The Military Aspect)
Series C - Subpanel III: International Economic and Social Objectives and Strategy (Foreign Economic Policy for the Twentieth Century)
Series D - Subpanel IV: U.S. Economic and Social Policy (The Challenge to America: Its Economic and Social Aspects)
Series E - Subpanel V: U.S. Utilization of Human Resources (The Pursuit of Excellence: Education and the Future of America)
Series F - Subpanel VI: U.S. Democratic Process (The Power of the Democratic Idea)
Series G - Subpanel VII: The Moral Framework of National Purpose (no report)
Series H - Subpanels VI and VII Joint Report-Writing Committee
Series I - Overall Panel
Series J - Office Reference and Report Publication Files
Series K - Special Formats
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select material restricted in accordance with the terms of donation, including material documenting the administration of the project.
- Special Studies Project, 1956-1964; 4; 28 Cubic Feet 70 boxes
  Biographical/Historical note
  The Rockefeller Brothers Fund Special Studies Project was inspired by Nelson Rockefeller, who served as President during most of the period of major activity. The purpose of the Special Studies was "to define the major problems and opportunities" facing the United States in the late 1950s, "to clarify national purposes and objectives...", and to develop principles which could serve as the basis of national policy.
  To effect this aim, Henry Kissinger was chosen to serve as Director. Mr. Kissinger coordinated the solicitation, criticism, and editing of papers from a host of specialists in many fields, including history, area studies, economics, political science, and sociology. Many of these papers were used, in some measure, as the basis of discussion by the subpanels for which the papers were written. The papers and discussion sessions resulted in final reports by each panel, and these reports were published under the title "Prospect for America: the Rockefeller Panel Reports."
  Scope and Contents note
  The records of the Rockefeller Brothers Fund Special Studies Project document the administrative and intellectual history of the project. The Special Studies Project collection constitutes a rich, but by no means comprehensive, source for the intellectual history of American domestic and foreign policy from 1945 to approximately 1960. Papers and criticisms of papers were contributed to the Project by leading academic and government authorities. Although an examination of these materials will not normally show the development over time of a writer's ideas, some files include a writer's older pieces. The papers prepared for the Special Studies Project are invariably thorough expositions of the contributor's views in the late 1950s.
  This study was undertaken in the latter 1950s and was published in 1960. A number of Project participants became members of the Kennedy Administration. In addition, letters and memoranda to and by Henry Kissinger, and editorial comments by Mr. Kissinger, appear throughout these records. Most of these items are of a routine administrative nature, but there are some letters and memoranda by Mr. Kissinger which include substantive comments about foreign policy and panel papers.
  Arrangement note
  The Special Studies Project record group is divided into ten series, listed below. The title that follows the subpanel number represents the name of the subpanel. The title in parentheses represents the title of the subpanel's report as it appears in "Prospect for America."
  Series A - Subpanel I: International Objectives and Strategies (The Mid-Century Challenge to U.S. Foreign Policy)
  Series B - Subpanel II: International Security Objectives and Strategy (International Security: The Military Aspect)
  Series C - Subpanel III: International Economic and Social Objectives and Strategy (Foreign Economic Policy for the Twentieth Century)
  Series D - Subpanel IV: U.S. Economic and Social Policy (The Challenge to America: Its Economic and Social Aspects)
  Series E - Subpanel V: U.S. Utilization of Human Resources (The Pursuit of Excellence: Education and the Future of America)
  Series F - Subpanel VI: U.S. Democratic Process (The Power of the Democratic Idea)
  Series G - Subpanel VII: The Moral Framework of National Purpose (no report)
  Series H - Subpanels VI and VII Joint Report-Writing Committee
  Series I - Overall Panel
  Series J - Office Reference and Report Publication Files
  Series K - Special Formats
  Related Archival Materials note
  FA324 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Rockefeller Boards, Series O contains a brief subseries for the Rockefeller Brothers Fund, which includes some material on the Special Studies Project. Both the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records and the Rockefeller Foundation records contain files concerning several of the Special Studies Project participants. Indexes may be checked for names that are of interest.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research with select material restricted in accordance with the terms of donation, including material documenting the administration of the project.
  - Subpanel I: International Objectives and Strategies, 1956-1964; A
    The files in this subseries are arranged into several sections: Organization, Membership, Papers, Meetings, and Reports. The Membership section is arranged alphabetically by the last name of the member. The Papers section and accompanying correspondence are arranged by arbitrarily-assigned paper numbers. The Meetings section and the Reports section are both arranged chronologically.
    This subseries contains correspondence, memoranda, papers, drafts, and final reports. Organization files, which are brief, concern the planning of subpanel activities. Membership files, as well as the correspondence that accompanies files in the Papers section, document discussions and writing on issues considered by the subpanel. The Papers files provide comprehensive presentations of the views of various subpanel experts on selected topics. Meeting files contain summaries and sometimes minute of subpanel discussions of issues. The Reports files, containing several drafts of each report, show the progressive synthesizing of the views of a subpanel's members.
    - Outline of Major Questions and Issues - Drafts of Memorandum, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Membership, 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Membership - Berle, Adolf, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Membership - Berle, Adolf, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Membership - Cantril, Hadley, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Membership - Cantril, Hadley, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Membership - Davis, Saville, 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Membership - Johnson, Joseph E., 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Membership - King, John Andrews, Jr. (Secretary), 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Membership - Nason, John W., 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Membership - Potofsky, Jacob S., 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Membership - Rockefeller, John D., 3rd, 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Membership - Rusk, Dean, 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Membership - Sarnoff, David, 1956-1961 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Membership - Spofford, Charles M., 1956-1961 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Papers, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Papers - Rostow, Walt W. - Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Papers - Rostow, Walt W. - Correspondence, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Papers - Rostow, Walt W. - Paper I-1 - "The National Interest", 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Papers - Rostow, Walt W. - Paper I-1a - "The Challenge Facing the United States", 1956 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Papers - Granger, Lester B. - Paper I-3 - "The Racial Factor in Our International Relations", 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Papers - Hilsman, Roger - Correspondence and Clippings, 1956-1961 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Papers - Hilsman, Roger - Paper I-4 - "Nuclear Technology and Alliances: An Analysis", 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Papers - Dexter, Byron - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Papers - Dexter, Byron - Paper I-5 - "Objectives and Alliances", 1956-1958 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Papers - Pettee, George S. - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Papers - Pettee, George S. - Paper I-6 - "Alliance as an Organizing Instrument", 1956-1958 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Papers - Rainey, Froelich - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Papers - Rainey, Froelich - Paper I-7 - "The Colonial Problem", 1956-1958 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Papers - Pye, Lucian - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Papers - Pye, Lucian - Paper I-8 - "American Policy and the Politics of Underdeveloped Countries", 1956-1958 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Papers - Nielsen, Waldemar - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Papers - Nielsen, Waldemar - Paper I-11 - "Energy and the Atlantic Alliance", 1956 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Papers - Whidden, Howard - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Papers - Whidden, Howard - Paper I-12 - "Europe at the Crossroads: The Next 10 to 15 Years", 1956-1958 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Papers - Strausz-Hupe, Robert - Correspondence and Papers, 1956-1963 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Papers - Strausz-Hupe, Robert - Paper I-13 - "Political Trends in NATO", 1956-1958 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Papers - Kraemer, Fritz - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Papers - Kraemer, Fritz - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Papers - Scammon, Richard - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Papers - Scammon, Richard - Paper I-15 - "Germany", 1956-1958 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Papers - Levitas, Samuel - Correspondence and Clippings, 1956-1961 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Papers - Levitas, Samuel - Paper I-16 - "The Role of the Anti-Communist 'Left' in Europe", 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Papers - McKeever, Porter - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Papers - McKeever, Porter - Paper I-17 - "Iceland", 1956 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Papers - Wood, Bryce - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Papers - Wood, Bryce - Paper I-19 - "The Policy of the United States Toward the Countries of South and Central America", 1956-1958 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Papers - Whitaker, Arthur P. - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Papers - Whitaker, Arthur P. - Paper I-20 - "The United States and Latin America", 1956-1958 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Papers - Linebarger, Paul - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Papers - Linebarger, Paul - Paper I-21 - "America, Japan and the Asian Nations", 1956 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Papers - Scalapino, Robert A. - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Papers - Scalapino, Robert A. - Paper I-22 - "The United States and Japan: Present Trends and Future Prospects", 1956-1958 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Papers - Walker, Richard - Correspondence, 1956-1963 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Papers - Walker, Richard - Paper I-23 - "China, the United States and the Continuing Struggle", 1956 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Papers - Boorman, Howard - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Papers - Boorman, Howard - Paper I-24 - "China at Mid-Century: Reassessment of a Dilemma", 1956-1958 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Papers - Ekvall, Robert B. - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Papers - Ekvall, Robert B. - Paper I-25 - "Some Considerations Pertinent to a China Policy", 1956-1958 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Papers - Stanton, Edwin F. - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - Papers - Stanton, Edwin F. - Paper I-26 - "United States Policies and Objectives...in Southeast Asia", 1956-1958 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - Papers - Phillips, William T. - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Papers - Phillips, William T. - Paper I-27 - "Problems and Trends in Southeast Asia", 1957 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Papers - Henderson, William - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Papers - Henderson, William - Paper I-28 - "United States Policy in Southeast Asia: The Case for a New Approach", 1957 (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - Papers - Henderson, William - Paper I-28a - "United States Policy in Southeast Asia: The Case for a New Approach", 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - Papers - Henderson, William - Paper I-28b - "United States Policy and the Security of Southeast Asia", 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 67)
    - Papers - Cady, John F. - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 5, Folder 68)
    - Papers - Cady, John F. - Paper I-29 - "India's Foreign Policy with Special Reference to United States Relations", 1956 (Box 6, Folder 69)
    - Papers - Thornburg, Max - Correspondence, Clippings, Papers, 1954-1964 (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - Papers - Thornburg, Max - Paper I-30 - "American Policy for the Middle East", 1956 (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Papers - Thornburg, Max - Paper I-30 - "American Policy for the Middle East", 1956-1958 (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Papers - Wright, Edwin M. - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - Papers - Wright, Edwin M. - Paper I-31 - "The Arab-Israeli Dispute", 1956-1958 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - Papers - Hurewitz, Jacob - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - Papers - Hurewitz, Jacob - Paper I-31a - "The Middle East After November 1956", 1956-1958 (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Papers - Cowan, L. Gray - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - Papers - Cowan, L. Gray - Paper I-32 - "The Political Evolution of West Africa", 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 78)
    - Papers - deKiewiet, Cornelis - Correspondence, 1956-1961, undated (Box 7, Folder 79)
    - Papers - deKiewiet, Cornelis - Paper I-33 - "Trends and Developments in South Africa", 1956-1958 (Box 7, Folder 80)
    - Papers - Dvorin, Eugene P. - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 7, Folder 81)
    - Papers - Dvorin, Eugene P. - Paper I-34 - "Central and Southern Africa", 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 82)
    - Papers - Rosberg, Carl - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 7, Folder 83)
    - Papers - Rosberg, Carl - Paper I-35 - "British East Africa: Problems and Prospects", 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 84)
    - Papers - Van Bilsen, Joseph - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 7, Folder 85)
    - Papers - Van Bilsen, Joseph - Paper I-36 - "The Congo and Its Future", 1957 (Box 7, Folder 86)
    - Papers - Barghoorn, Frederick - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 7, Folder 87)
    - Papers - Barghoorn, Frederick - Paper I-38 - "Soviet Domestic Developments and the Future of Soviet-American Relations", 1956-1958 (Box 7, Folder 88)
    - Papers - Fainsod, Merle - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - Papers - Fainsod, Merle - Paper I-39 - "Soviet Internal Developments Over the Next Decade", 1956-1958 (Box 7, Folder 90)
    - Papers - Rostow, Walt - Paper I-40 - "Notes on Change in the Soviet Union", 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 91)
    - Papers - Spulber, Nicolas - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 7, Folder 92)
    - Papers - Spulber, Nicolas - Paper I-42 - "Soviet Economic Growth, Trade, and Aid and the Soviet Penetration Into the Underdeveloped Areas", 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 93)
    - Papers - Free, Lloyd - Correspondence, 1956-1962 (Box 8, Folder 94)
    - Papers - Millikan, Max - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 8, Folder 95)
    - Papers - Mosely, Philip - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 8, Folder 96)
    - Papers - Possony, Stefan - Correspondence, 1956-1958 (Box 8, Folder 97)
    - Meetings - Issues, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 98)
    - Meetings - Agendas, Minutes, Memoranda - Meetings 1 and 2, 1956 November 21, December 18 (Box 8, Folder 99)
    - Meetings - Agendas, Minutes, Memoranda - Meetings 3 and 4, 1957 January 8, February 12 (Box 8, Folder 100)
    - Meetings - Agendas, Minutes, Memoranda - Meetings 5 and 6, 1957 February 28 - April 26 (Box 8, Folder 101)
    - Meetings - Steering Group - Meetings 1-3, 1959 May 27 - August 3 (Box 8, Folder 102)
    - Report Drafts - Correspondence, 1957-1959 (Box 8, Folder 103)
    - Report Drafts - King, John A., 1957 April (Box 8, Folder 104)
    - Report Drafts - Cooke, Dwight, 1957 May 5 (Box 8, Folder 105)
    - Report Drafts - King, John A., 1957 May 18 (Box 8, Folder 106)
    - Report Drafts - King, John A., 1957 July 12 (Box 8, Folder 107)
    - Report Drafts - Hecksher, August, 1959 July 27 (Box 9, Folder 108)
    - Report Drafts - Kintner, William B., 1957 August 15 (Box 9, Folder 109)
    - Report Drafts - Berle, Adolfe A., 1957 August 29 (Box 9, Folder 110)
    - Report Drafts - Berle, Adolfe A., 1957 September 25 (Box 9, Folder 111)
    - Report Drafts - Berle, Adolfe A., 1957 October 3 - 1958 April 9 (Box 9, Folder 112)
    - Report Drafts - Berle, Adolfe A., 1957 December 18 (Box 9, Folder 113)
    - Report Drafts - Barnett, 1958 February 17 (Box 9, Folder 114)
    - Report Drafts - Hecksher, August, 1959 June 18 (Box 9, Folder 115)
    - Report Drafts - Hecksher, August, 1959 August 11 (Box 9, Folder 116)
    - Report Drafts - Hecksher, August, 1959 September 4 (Box 9, Folder 117)
    - Report Drafts - Hecksher, August, 1959 October 1 (Box 10, Folder 118)
    - Report Drafts - Comments - Draft of May 18, 1957 - Comments by Various People, June 1957 (Box 10, Folder 119)
    - Report Drafts - Comments - Draft of October 30, 1959 - Comments by Adolf Berle, 1959 October 30 (Box 10, Folder 120)
    - Report Drafts - Comments - Draft of October 30, 1959 - Comments by Henry Kissinger, 1959 October 30 (Box 10, Folder 121)
    - Report Drafts - Comments - Draft of October 30, 1959 - Comments by John Gardner, Laurance Rockefeller, Dean Rusk, 1959 October 30 (Box 10, Folder 122)
    - Report Drafts - Comments - Draft of October 30, 1959 - Comments by Elizabeth Hawley, Johnson, 1959 October 30 (Box 10, Folder 123)
    - Report Drafts - Comments - Comments Collated, 1959 November (Box 10, Folder 124)
    - Report Drafts - Comments - Comments Collated, 1959 November 30 (Box 11, Folder 125)
    - Report - Endorsements, 1959 November (Box 11, Folder 126)
    - Report Drafts - Publication, 1959 November (Box 11, Folder 127)
    - Report Drafts - Publication - Galley Proofs, 1959 November (Box 11, Folder 128)
    - Report Summary - Drafts, 1959 November (Box 11, Folder 129)
    - Summaries and Publicity - Publicity, 1959 December 7 (Box 11, Folder 130)
  - Subpanel II: International Security Objectives and Strategy, 1956-1964; B
    - Issues, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 131)
    - Membership - Altschul, Frank, 1956-1961 (Box 12, Folder 132)
    - Membership - Anderson, Frederick L., 1956-1961 (Box 12, Folder 133)
    - Membership - Bendetsen, Karl R., 1957-1961 (Box 12, Folder 134)
    - Membership - Bronk, Detlev W., 1956-1961 (Box 12, Folder 135)
    - Membership - Dean, Gordon E., 1956-1961 (Box 12, Folder 136)
    - Membership - Fisk, James B., 1956-1961 (Box 12, Folder 137)
    - Membership - Floberg, John F., 1956-1961 (Box 12, Folder 138)
    - Membership - Gaylord, Bradley, 1956-1961 (Box 12, Folder 139)
    - Membership - Hoopes, Townsend W. (Secretary), 1956-1961 (Box 12, Folder 140)
    - Membership - Land, Edwin H., 1957 (Box 12, Folder 141)
    - Membership - Luce, Henry R., 1956-1961 (Box 12, Folder 142)
    - Membership - McCormack, James (Chairman), 1955-1957 (Box 12, Folder 143)
    - Membership - McCormack, James (Chairman), 1958-1961 (Box 12, Folder 144)
    - Membership - Nash, Frank, 1956-1961 (Box 12, Folder 145)
    - Membership - Rockefeller, Laurance S. (Chairman, Overall Panel), 1956-1964 (Box 13, Folder 146)
    - Membership - Teller, Edward, 1956-1957 (Box 13, Folder 147)
    - Membership - Teller, Edward, 1958-1963 (Box 13, Folder 148)
    - Membership - Wilson, Carrol L., 1956-1958 (Box 13, Folder 149)
    - Papers - Johnson, Ellis A. - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 13, Folder 150)
    - Papers - Johnson, Ellis A. - Paper II-3 - "The Problem of Nuclear Weapons", 1957 (Box 13, Folder 151)
    - Papers - Pettee, George S. - Paper II-2 - "The Making of National Security Plans and Decisions According to the Manner and Style of the Americans", 1957 (Box 13, Folder 152)
    - Papers - Walkowicz, T. F. - Correspondence, 1956-1963 (Box 13, Folder 153)
    - Papers - Walkowicz, T. F. - Paper II-4 - "Survival in an Age of Technological Contest", 1957 (Box 13, Folder 154)
    - Papers - Kintner, William R. - Correspondence, 1956-1959 (Box 14, Folder 155)
    - Papers - Kintner, William R. - Correspondence, 1959-1965 (Box 14, Folder 156)
    - Papers - Kintner, William R. - Paper II-5 - "The Communist Strategy of Protracted Conflict", 1956-1957 (Box 14, Folder 157)
    - Papers - Cross, James E. - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 14, Folder 158)
    - Papers - Cross, James E. - Paper II-6 - "Political Instability in Underdeveloped Areas", 1956-1957 (Box 14, Folder 159)